Another day, another new world's
smartest model. Gemini 3.1 Pro just
dropped. And honestly, it is kind of
crazy. All of the numbers I've been
seeing are insane. Both the ones Google
published and the ones being published
externally, as well as the ones I've
gotten myself. I've been using this
model a ton, running against every
benchmark. And the numbers are
incredible. It scored four points higher
on the artificial intelligence index
than any model before it, including Opus
4.6 Max. What's even crazier, though, is
it cost less than half as much to get
that score at only $892 versus the
almost $2500 that Opus 4.6 six cost.
Google's own numbers show it crushing
everything, including ARC AGI 2, which
just getting a 78% on ARC AGI 2 is
insane. The whole point of that one was
that Loom couldn't do it and AGI 1 was
be Oh god, no. This is insane. Like, all
of these numbers are nuts. So, is that
it? Is Opus dead? Has Google officially
won the AI wars? Not quite. None of
these things are this simple. As you
guys know, there's a lot more depth to
the numbers than there seems to be
online. And I cannot wait to go through
all of this with you guys right after a
quick word from today's sponsor. You
know how it feels like your AI gets way
better when you give it access to your
whole codebase instead of just trying to
scope it to a file? It turns out it goes
way further if you give it access to the
internet. It can do so much, especially
with all these new browser use agents.
But what browser are you going to let
them use? Probably not the one on your
computer, right? Especially for
programmatic realwork use cases. That's
why I'm so hyped about today's sponsor,
Kernel. The best place to run your
browser use agents in the cloud. Their
open source infrastructure is absurdly
fast. It takes less than 30 milliseconds
for them to spin up a browser that you
can connect to. And the actual process
of doing that couldn't be simpler.
Cloudset 4.6 is way better at browser
use than previous models. And it's
actually been really fun to play with.
This code will actually spin up a
browser with kernel and then give access
to claude so that it can run and do
things on it. We're going to have it
take a screenshot of the current page,
search around to find the blogs about
manage o, and then read and summarize
the blog post. And it does this by
actually navigating the site. Now all I
have to do is run our dev command and a
browser will be launched in the cloud.
You can even spin up a live view if you
want to that will show you what's
happening as it actually occurs. I have
my cursor there, but you can see there's
a mouse cursor there. If I want, I can
take over and do things, but I don't
need to. I'm letting the agent do it.
So, it just found and clicked on the
blog. It's decided to scroll, and now
it's finding the post that we were
talking about in the prompt. And if we
look here, you can see what Claude
decided to do each step along the way.
You can probably already see how useful
this is, but once you add in things like
persisting off, capture workarounds, and
all the other stuff you need, it becomes
a genuinely useful way to do things that
might not have an API. Stop limiting
your agents and what they're capable of
and give them access to the web at
soyb.link/kernel.
Back to it. We need to talk about Gemini
3.1 Pro. As I said before, I've been
using it a ton. I currently have it
running in the background porting an old
app. I've been using it in a ton of
different harnesses and a ton of
different like tools and building a
bunch of different stuff as well. I also
used it to update some old projects. And
in doing such, I have learned to deeply
deeply hate the Gemini CLI. Not only did
the Gemini CLI not have Gemini 3.1 on
day one, and I actually accidentally ran
this with Gemini 3, it looks like.
Great. Love that. Not only do they not
have 3.1 Pro on the CLI, it also just
breaks all the time. It is super buggy
and does just weird [__]
I was intentionally trying to preserve
this history so I could show you guys
some of the weird stuff, but uh since my
resolution changed on my computer, that
appears to have died. Great. Well, I'm
sure there will be plenty of issues with
this run. Let's take a quick look. You
know what? Actually, first things first,
because I accidentally ran Gemini 3 Pro
before, I got used to Gemini 3's
horrible inability to like do basic tool
calling correctly and consistently.
Almost the entire time that it was
running, it was hitting errors that made
no sense at all. Just like failing to
edit a file it had just read by passing
bad syntax. It seems like 3.1 is
significantly less bad about that, at
least from the official logs for this
particular run I am doing right now.
Since I couldn't use it in the official
CLI, I decided to first try it in the
cursor one, and it was insightful. The
cursor CLI actually seems decent so far.
I have my issues with it. You can't
paste images, which sucks, but otherwise
it seems to work. So, let's do a test
example here. Telling it to move from
SQLite to Postgress. I'm not actually
going to have it do that, but just see
how this goes. So, you guys can see some
of these thinking traces. Taking its
sweet, sweet time. Reconnecting. Great.
Good start. Uh, I don't know if this is
cursor's fault or Gemini's fault, but
whichever it is, this is a bad
experience. So, let's try again. You
might also notice that my top nav is
visible, and it normally isn't. This is
a bit of a tangent, but I want to
complain. So, I'm going to show you guys
that when I go to settings, my whole
computer breaks. And now, this is what
my Mac settings look like. I am so done
with Mac OS. Okay, it aggressively hides
the thinking right after showing it to
me in the cursor tool. So, I'll show you
here. Every single time it runs, it has
a prioritizing tool selection step. I've
been focusing on tool selection, leaning
heavily on specialized tools when
available. I'm actively avoiding CAT for
file manipulation, particularly when
other and it gets cut off. I've seen
this in everything that is correctly
using Gemini. These models suck at tool
calls. They just don't do them well.
They can be handed a bunch of tools,
smile and wave, and then not do anything
unless you put a ton of work instructing
them into using those tools. And if
you're not careful, they'll instead
massively overuse them. The reason why
I'm using cursor here is because of this
specifically. They've put a ton of time
into tuning the Gemini models into well,
I don't know how other than sucking
less. Google just does not seem like
they are training these models to be
good in harnesses. They are too focused
on benchmaxing. And oh boy, have they
benchmaxed. A while back, I made a
benchmark called skate bench that was
meant to measure how well different
models could name skateboarding tricks
based on descriptions of the tricks.
It's a combination of like a weird niche
knowledge bench as well as a spatial
recognition bench because you need to
know about the rotations and how it
affects the board and the skater and the
relationship between all of those
things. When I first made this
benchmark, Gro 4 had the highest score
by far in like the high7s. Okay, 75 is
what it got on my most recent run. And
then I went to the OpenAI office to try
out GPT5, which scored a 98, which just
absolutely broke me at the time. Since
then, OpenAI models have actually
regressed quite a bit, and the highest I
can get one of the modern ones to do is
about an 87, which is insane that it has
regressed that meaningfully. Obviously,
5.2 and 5.3 are phenomenal models for
code. They were not as good at this.
Take that as you will. We have a new
winner, and it's not close. Gemini 3.1
Pro Preview consistently hits 100% on
this benchmark. I don't know what the
hell they did, but it gets 3D very, very
well. It's also good at 2D space. It's
the first model to make an actually like
decent, usable SVG of the Pelican on a
bike. It took 323.9
seconds of thinking, but it did a pretty
good job here. Not only can it make
these SVGs, it can actually animate
them. Like, I've never seen a model
capable of this type of thing. SVG
animations are an intricate science that
is not easy to do. And yeah, it killed
it with a lot of this. I was even
setting it up on a couple other projects
I was working on and was impressed with
it animation capabilities. Personally, I
was not as impressed with the SVGs it
was creating, but I was able to make it
do some cool looking stuff. If you've
been around the last few weeks, you know
that I've taken on far too many side
projects. I'm close to wrapping up a few
of them and shipping them, and I might
have picked up one or two more. I want
to touch on a few quick though, because
I've been using Gemini for it, and there
are things that has done really well, as
well as things that has done really
poorly. One of the things it's doing
incredibly well is design. I'm working
on a new video review service, like code
review, but for video is an alternative
to frame, cuz I'm tired of Adobe stuff.
And it made a stunning homepage. I was
trying to get do some fancy stuff with
the layering of the images, but failed
there. So, I told it screw it. You have
these pieces. Go redesign it, make it
look decent. This was the first thing it
spit out. I obviously gave it
suggestions on how to tidy up a few
things from there. But, like, it made a
goodlook website without a whole lot of
work. I already had a site here that
wasn't great, and I told it to basically
unscrew it, and it did. It made like I'm
probably going to ship this as is. I'm
very happy with how this came out. It
also helped build this UI for a new
project that I'm working on that I'll
share a lot more about soon. I'm very
excited about this one. I have these
models effectively playing a game of
Quiplash against each other where
everything is generated. And I have been
surprised at how funny Gemini 3.1 Pro
has been. I also built this whole app
with Gemini 3.1 Pro. It had its quirks.
It definitely struggled when the length
of the task got bigger and I had to help
it unblock itself a lot. Like that's
funny. A plight thing to scream at
scarecrows. Nice flannel. Sorry about
the bird [__] Like that was decently
funny. And I'm not the only one who
thinks it's funny. The models do, too.
See that? Apparently, it's the funniest
model. I never would have expected that
Google would be the one to make
something funny. I honestly thought
Grock would do a bit better. I've
actually been surprised multiple times
where I looked at the two responses when
it was Grock versus Gemini, and Gemini
was the one making the more vile jokes.
To be fair, the first UI it made was a
ugly would be putting it lightly. It
also had a lot of quirks when I was
running it. I originally wrote this as a
CLI app. And man, I saw a lot of weird
Geminiisms when I did. This one was
funny because the GLM5 prompt writer
failed, so they didn't get prompted with
an actual thing they had to respond to.
They were told to be funny in the system
prompt, so Grock did its classic.
Jeffrey Epste didn't kill himself. And
then Gemini 3.1 Pro went with the Yeah,
this is the thing about the Gemini
models. They don't really behave well. I
don't mean that they like go off the
rails and do nasty stuff. I mean they
might do that a little bit. I've
definitely seen Gemini 3.1 Pro deleting
things it shouldn't be. I just had that
happen yesterday actually where it nuked
a bunch of assets that it was not
supposed to touch. Be careful when
you're giving it file write access for
sure. But the more annoying thing is
just the way it fails to perform as a
freaking model. Like it just doesn't do
it right. The amount of times I've seen
it just get stuck in like two-word loops
where it just says the same two words
over and over again or respond with
utter nonsense and immediately stop or
just like switch over to Chinese
characters, which would happen a lot
with Gemini 3 Pro. Haven't had that with
3.1 yet, but I have all of the other
quirks and then some. Here's another
funny one. In the system prompt for the
model that is making the prompt that the
other models use to respond to, I know
prompt means two different things here.
It's confusing. The system prompt I
wrote to give the model so it could
generate a game prompt to use for the
other models. That system prompt says
that it should only return the thing it
wants to have the other models respond
to. It says return only this thing,
which Gemini did by saying return only.
This is like llama 2 [__] But this is
the nature of the Gemini models. They
are insanely smart. The amount of
intelligence they've baked into these
models is honestly overwhelming. I am
consistently surprised by how competent
it is in knowledge. And I'm not the only
one that feels that way. Artificial
Analysis has commented on the same
specifically around the hallucination
rates and it's just knowledge in
general. Artificial analysis made their
own omniscience benchmark that is
keeping track of knowledge and
hallucinations and letting them cancel
each other out. So you're ranked both by
how many answers you got correctly as
well as how many times you answer
incorrectly. And you're not penalized
for refusing to answer for saying I
don't know. So this is a benchmark that
rewards models that are able to say I
don't know what the answer to that is.
punishes them if they lie a lot and then
obviously rewards them if they do the
problem correctly. And as we can see
here, 3.1 Pro Preview had a really good
score. Even some of the smartest models
like Sonnet 4.6 and GPT 5.2 high are
still in the negatives because this
benchmark has a lot of really hard
problems that the models will often
hallucinate and get incorrectly. If we
hop over to the hallucination rate chart
though, you'll see previous models like
Gemini 3 Flash and GPTOSS20B
were insanely high. When they didn't
know the answer, they would never
refuse. they would just be wrong.
Surprisingly enough, Haiku 4.5 is the
model that is the best about this. It's
very quick to say when it doesn't know
something. Gemini 3. Preview though is a
huge advancement here. It is a comical
gap between 3.1 Pro and 3 Pro where the
hallucidation rate has nearly hald in
that time. But where Google really
slaughters in these benchmarks is the
accuracy. It just knows more
information. So, it's able to answer a
lot more of these questions correct than
even other leading models. It's
obviously such an intelligent model. The
amount of information, the amount of
capability baked into these weights is
unreal. But when it comes to actually
using it, it genuinely sucks. Some part
of that is just the way it randomly
spams my terminals after I close things
for no reason. I have no idea what's
going on here at all. We're just going
to close that terminal entirely. Why did
it do that? Okay. I am genuinely trying
so hard to use Gemini 3.1 Pro to test
things. But no matter what the [__] I do
in their CLI, it just randomly changes
to other models. Why is it using Flash
Light, Flash 2.5, and three Flash
preview? When I selected Gemini 3.1 Pro,
their CLI is legitimately unusable. And
as silly as it sounds, I think that's a
big part of why it sucks as hard as it
does. It's pretty clear now that the
other labs are using the histories from
other people's chats to train models. If
you have a before and an after, if you
have the thing that somebody needed
changed in the changes they made in the
before and after for that repo, it's
pretty easy to generate a fake history
for any of these CLIs. Once the labs
have generated all of these fake
histories, they use it for reinforcement
learning. And the result is that the
models can work in these tools and they
can work in them really well for really
long amounts of time. Google doesn't
seem to be doing this at all. I could be
wrong. They're clearly rling on
something, but it's not helping with
these long agentic runs. The meter eval
show what I'm talking about here really
strongly. If you're not familiar, this
is a benchmark that tracks how long of a
task in terms of the human time to
complete are the models capable of
completing. At the start of 2025, the
best we had was between half an hour to
an hour of a task being able to be
completed by an agent on its own 50% of
the time. This is 50% success rate. Now
with Opus 4.6, we're up all the way to
the 16-hour range where it can run on a
task for a very long time. Obviously, it
won't be 16 hours. It'll be closer to
like half an hour to an hour, but it's a
task that would have taken a human 16
plus hours with a 50% success rate.
That's nuts. Both GBT 5.2 and Opus 4.6
are killing it here. And once 5.3 is on
the API, I would suspect it will kill
here as well. I don't think Gemini
models are capable of performing well on
this because they tend to get really
confused and lost when given the ability
to like go do things for a while. I also
said earlier it seemed like the tool
call issues had mostly stopped. I can't
know that because it just ran with the
wrong [__] model. So yeah, I'm now
rerunning this yet again with 3.1 Pro
preview. Hopefully it will actually stay
on the model I selected this time. I
couldn't help but notice there isn't a
plan mode. And I also just accidentally
turned off yellow mode. Great. The CLI
is awful. Obviously, CLI is awful. We
all know that. Just use anything else if
you can. Oh man, I I just need to
complain a bit about this dissonance
between how smart these models are and
how competent they are. I'm going to do
a strange comparison. I want to talk
about Claude 4.5 Haiku. Why would I want
to talk about Haiku? It's a super dumb
model. If we go to the intelligence
index on top here, you'll see it's not
even in the main chart because why would
it be? It's scoring a 37. And these
models are in the high50s now. Why would
I want to talk about this tiny cheap
[__] model? Because it does its godamn
job. And this is the thing I want to
emphasize. Models aren't just bundles of
knowledge. They're also now expected to
have behaviors and to do things,
especially with tool calling and
especially with knowledge gathering
through the tool calling. Obviously, a
model with more knowledge is going to be
able to do more things in general. If
it's smarter, it knows more and it's
able to do more. But if it's able to
gather knowledge better, that tends to
push it ahead quite a bit. And what
Anthropic has been super focused on from
at least the Sonnet 35 days onwards is
the consistency around the tool calling.
I never see Haiku screw up the shape of
a tool call. If you tell it how a tool
works, it will use it and it will use it
relatively well. If you ask Gemini 3.1
Pro Preview to use a tool, it will
rotate between using it too much, not
using it at all, and using it
incorrectly with the occasional correct
usage. Although it is rare, the model
clearly follows instructions better
overall than it has in the past. Like
Google has made some progress here, but
it still honestly feels like a lastg
model. It feels like somebody took
something from like the old llama days
or even one of like the older deepseek
openweight models and stuffed infinite
intelligence into it, but forgot to put
the competence in. It's just not good at
doing things. They don't have a plan
tool, but what I've heard from others is
that in the harnesses that do have a
plan tool, it'll just not use it. It'll
just output the questions and you're
expected to just answer and then it will
create a bunch of output and say are you
happy with this and you say yes or no.
It doesn't call the plan tool or any of
the things that are associated with it.
My guess is that they tried to RL it on
a planning phase but didn't RL it on a
planning phase with planning tools and
as a result it just is weird. Okay, it
looks like it wrote a decent plan here
but again not in plan mode. Telling it
to go work. Okay, it still has the
random failing to edit thing. Like I
don't know how it screws this type of
stuff up. It also sucks at reading
files. It seems like it was hardcoded to
only be able to read up to a 100 lines
at a time. And I've watched it read line
one through 100, 101 to 200, 2011 to 300
on many different things. Like why? I
feel like I have to sit there and watch
this model not just so I can cover it
responsibly for you guys, but so I can
make sure it's not breaking constantly
and doing things wrong. Cuz that's all
inference you're paying for. Is it more
efficient when it does everything
correctly? Yeah, it's cheaper and uses
slightly fewer tokens than something
like Opus 4.6, but if it has to generate
3x the number of tokens because it
failed the tool call the first two
times, you're not benefiting as much any
at all at that point. Like, I've never
seen any of the other modern models fail
so often with basic stuff like that.
Even the new open weight ones seem to
have resolved a lot of these things.
Google just hasn't. Trying to reach
Gemini 3.1 Pro preview attempt three of
three. It's about to fail as it was just
getting started. H you'd imagine the
trillion dollar company would be the one
that could figure these things out. Like
this has to be solvable with money and
time and smart engineering, right? I
just don't get how it could get as bad
as it currently is. When I was working
on the game I showed earlier, I wanted
the logos for all of the labs and it
just h the reasoning summaries are just
so bad. I've been on a quest to explore
various language models. ChatGpt is
definitely a strong contender. Now I'm
shifting my attention to locating
Claude, Deepseek, and Grock. My focus is
on understanding their capabilities and
how they might differ from Chhat GBT.
No, it's [__] not. I told you to go
find Logos. I don't know why they're
hiding the reasoning traces. They're not
that useful anymore. And this is the
alternative is garbage. I don't know
what happened here. Was the reasoning
actually that bad and we got a summary
that summarized the bad thing it was
doing or was the summarization process
incorrect that gave us this nonsense?
Because again, remember I asked it to go
find logos for the things in the
codebase and it somehow went on a
soularching journey all about chat GPT.
And in any competent harness where it
has tools it actually uses well, they've
system prompted the hell out of it and
you see the labbotomized results. I'm
currently evaluating the best approach
to use various tools for this task. It's
a complex process. So I am being very
deliberate in assessing which tools will
be the most suitable. I'm focusing on
the particular strengths of each tool to
ensure maximum efficiency. This was for
a simple UI change. It just it's
honestly been flashbacks to like early
2025, hell, late 2024 where I feel like
I have to be closely monitoring what
it's doing and I see it just doing
things wrong constantly.
Oh, I didn't realize the reason it
wasn't able to reach 3.1 Pro because I
had to go give it permission to run this
command because it didn't know it needed
to have that. And now I think the CLI is
broken again. Oh no, it's spawning more
things. It looks like it hallucinated
packages that don't exist. So much for
that lower hallucination rate. It has
access to the web. It can look these
things up. I told it what to do and how
to do it, and it has just outright
failed to do it. It's writing a Python
code mod to do the code mod itself
because it didn't succeed in finding it.
This is a company that made the world's
biggest and most successful search
engine, and it can't figure out where
the code mod is that I told it about. It
does seem to be pretty good at using
additional knowledge it is given. So, if
you put things in the system prompt or
the instructions or just in the context,
it's able to adjust its behavior
meaningfully. You've probably heard me
talk about Convex is by far my favorite
way to handle backend stuff nowadays.
They have an LLM leaderboard for how
well the different models work with
Convex. They have two versions. They
have the with guidelines where they're
given the Convex AI rules and they have
a separate no guidelines version where
they aren't. When not given guidelines,
Claude 4.6 sonnet slaughters. It just
seems like Anthropic snuck this into the
training data. I don't know why or how,
but yeah, it performed very well at a
90% there when compared to GPT 5.2, my
beloved, only getting a 75%. This is one
of the many reasons I keep reaching for
anthropic models. But now, Gemini scored
great here at an 89%. But what was even
crazier is when you turn on those
guidelines, suddenly we're almost at a
95. It is way better at convex than
basically anything else available right
now. And as someone who uses Convex a
lot, this is super tempting. I want to
play with this more because it got the
fundamentals, data modeling perfect,
queries nearly perfect, mutations
perfect, actions perfect, idioms
perfect, and the highest client score
we've seen to date. Like that's huge.
When it's given these rules, it
meaningfully increases its likelihood of
being correct. At the same time though,
it is scoring horribly with stuff like
SnitchBench. If you're not familiar with
SnitchBench, it's a benchmark I made
because people didn't seem to understand
part of the reporting anthropic did
where they talked about the model doing
things that the controller of it might
not want it to do that it thought was
morally correct and the dangers of that.
This was misunderstood by a bunch of
people thinking that Anthropic made it
intentionally do that. So, I made a
benchmark that replicated that to show
people that a lot of models do it,
including Grock 4.1. All the Grock
models are hardcore snitches for
whatever reason. I also just realized
when I had Gemini redo the UI for
SnitchBench, it screwed up the sort
order. It's supposed to put the sum of
the two shifted to the left. So Grock
4.1 is the worst snitch and Gemini 3.1
Pro is the second worst snitch where it
will set on you to the government 100%
of the time and it'll send on you to the
media 30% in this particular scenario.
And that's the tame version. I have two
treatments for this particular
benchmark. One where it is told not to
act any specific way, just what to do
with all of the emails of the medical
malpractice it's seeing. And then the
bold version where I tell it to act
boldly and in the interest of humanity,
which bumps it to a perfect 100% on both
government and media, making it by far
the worst snitch we have ever seen on
this benchmark. It is the only model
I've ever seen get a perfect score on
all of my benches. It got 100% snitch to
the government. It got 100% snitch to
media. And it got 100% on Skate Bench,
too. Like, it's silly, but I find this
honestly telling. the model benchmarks
so hard that it's winning the benchmarks
that it probably doesn't want to. But
yeah, I can't find any way to measure
this model where it doesn't come out
number one or near number one, but then
when I actually try to use it, it just
sucks to use. That's the jarring
contrast that I'm trying to emphasize to
y'all. On one hand, this model knows
more than any other technology that's
ever been made in the past. It's nuts
how intelligent it is. But on the other
hand, it feels like we're going back in
time where I handed it this migration
that a dozen models have been able to do
now. and it got stuck and thinks that
it's in a potential loop. The Gemini
models are the only models that loop
enough and fail enough that they had to
put a potential loop was detected hook
into their CLI because it happens so
often. I'll tell it to continue. God,
it's it's so bad. If you have an
unlimited token budget and you love
playing with these things, it's
definitely worth playing with it a bit.
Like, it's really really intelligent.
And if you want to try out this model
without spending a whole bunch of money,
I highly recommend you check out what
we've built at T3 Chat. You can get the
best out of Gemini 3.1 Pro, specifically
its knowledge, without having to pay
Google a ton of money for a subscription
that you're only using every once in a
while to ask it a question, and you'll
still have access to all of the other
much more consistent models when you
want to use those for other things. This
last week has been our launch week for
T3 chat. We shipped a ton of features,
so if you haven't used it in a while,
definitely check it out again. We even
have a higher tier finally for those of
you guys who want to do basically
endless prompting. 50 bucks a month for
unlimited effectively and it's still
only eight bucks a month for a very
generous base tier. But if you're
looking for something for code, I still
recommend Codeex 5.3. The plan is too
generous. The model's really good and
you don't get a lot of these quirks. I
have had to tab in and say yes far too
many times to this very, very special
model. On February 13th, I said that I
wish Google would stop benchmaxing for
long enough to make a usable model.
Gemini 3 Pro is as smart as Opus, but it
screws up tool calls as consistently as
Gro 3 Mini. Crazy to think I said this
over a week ago and it's more true now
than ever. Google, make your models
work. Stop trying to win every
benchmark. There's more important things
and the models are just not usable yet.
Go have your engineers try other models
and use other things and they'll quickly
come back with exactly what needs to
change because right now it is just not
pleasant to use. I got nothing else to
say on this one. Until next time, peace
nerds.